Finding aid for Marvin Lemmon Niehuss Papers, 1923-1972 (bulk 1941-1968)
Bentley Historical Library
Marvin Lemmon Niehuss papers
1923-1972
1941-1968
Bentley Historical Library
Niehuss, Marvin Lemmon, 1903-
852068 Aa 2
28.5 linear feet
University of Michigan professor of law, 1936-1944 and 1968-1972, vice president for university relations, 1944-1951, vice president and dean of faculties, 1951-1962, and executive vice president, 1962-1967. Papers include correspondence and reports concerning University affairs and some course materials from Niehuss' law classes. Included here are files relating to Niehuss' involvement in the University decision to fire three professors investigated by the House Un-American Activities Committee, and in the review of the University's compliance to the Civil Rights Act of 1964.
The collection was donated by Marvin L. Niehuss and Margaret Niehuss Munchmeyer (Donor no. 4637 ) in 1968 and 1992. 2000 accession was transferred from the University of Michigan Law School (Donor no. 343 ).
The collection is open to research with the exception of a folder of material relating to admissions with student identifiable information.
Copyright was transferred to the University of Michigan.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
Marvin Lemmon Niehuss was associated with the University of Michigan for over fifty years, starting as an undergraduate in 1920, earning his bachelor's and law degrees in 1925 and 1930 respectively, and eventually serving in a variety of capacities: researcher, law professor, and administrator. His most notable role was legislative relations specialist for the university administration.
Niehuss was born in Lexington, Kentucky and raised in Mississippi. Except for two years practicing law in Chicago during the 1930s, his entire career was devoted to the University of Michigan. He made the move from law professor to administrator during World War II, when he coordinated government contracts for the university as Vice President for University Relations. From 1951 to 1962 he served as Vice President and Dean of Faculties, and from 1962 to 1968, as Executive Vice President.
Among the most pressing issues Niehuss dealt with were enrollment bulges in the late 1940s and 1960s, "cash crises" during the 1950s, and affirmative action issues in the 1960s. He also actively supported the dismissal of three alleged communists on faculty (Professors Nickerson, Davis and Markert) who were questioned by the House Un-American Activities Committee in 1954.
Niehuss retired from administration to resume teaching responsibilities at the Law School in 1968, and was named Professor Emeritus of Law in June 1973. He died in Louisville, KY May 3, 2003
Niehuss Appointments (University of Michigan)
1925 A.B.
1930 LL.B.
1927-1928, 1930-1931 Instructor in Economics
1928-1929, 1931 Research Assistant, Business Administration
1931-1932 Instructor in Real Estate
1933-1934 Instructor in Law
1934-1936 Private Legal Practice
1936-1944 Associate Professor of Law
1942-1945 Coordinator, Division for Emergency Training
1944 Professor of Law
1944-1951 Vice President for University Relations
1951-1962 Vice President and Dean of Faculties
1962-1968 Executive Vice President
1968-1972 Professor of Law
The Marvin Niehuss Papers document his career as Law School faculty member and university administrator. The papers include correspondence and reports concerning University affairs and some course materials from Niehuss' law classes. Included here are files relating to Niehuss' involvement in the University decision to fire three professors investigated by the House Un-American Activities Committee, and in the review of the University's compliance to the Civil Rights Act of 1964.
The Niehuss papers have arrived in three separate accessions. Researchers should be aware that there is significant overlap within the three accessions. Specific topics can be tracked across the various accessions. The papers are organized into two series: a small Miscellaneous File, 1945-1951, and Topical Files, 1923-1972.
Academic freedom.; Civil rights -- Michigan.; Affirmative action programs -- Michigan.; Davis, Chandler.; Delta College.; Ford Foundation.; Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (University of Michigan-Wayne State University); Markert, Clement L. (Clement Lawrence), 1917-1999.; Michigan Council of State College Presidents.; Michigan Health Council.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Nickerson, Mark.; Niehuss, Marvin Lemmon, 1903-2003.; University of Michigan -- Administration.; University of Michigan -- Admission.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Higher Education.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan.; University of Michigan. Development Council.; University of Michigan. Executive Vice-President.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan.; University of Michigan. Institute of Industrial Health.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan -- Law School.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Senate.; University of Michigan. Sesquicentennial Celebration.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan. Vice-President and Dean of Faculties.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for University Relations.; University of Michigan -- Anniversaries, etc.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.
- Miscellaneous Files, 1945-1951
  - Ann Arbor, City of (Box 1)
  - Biographical Article (Box 1)
  - Building Program at the University of Michigan, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Colleges (Box 1)
  - Conference of Governing Boards (Box 1)
  - Cooley Foundation (Box 1)
  - Discrimination in Campus Organizations (Box 1)
  - Fees Committee (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 1)
  - Hospital School (Box 1)
  - Legislature (Box 1)
  - Legislature--Building Construction (Box 1)
  - Medical Center (Box 1)
  - Medical School (Box 1)
  - Michigan Crippled Children Commission (Box 1)
  - Provost's Report to the Board of Regents (Box 1)
  - Residence Halls (Box 1)
  - Student Affairs (Box 1)
  - Subversive Activities Report (Box 1)
  - University Hospital--Committee on Selection of a Director, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - University Lectures (Box 1)
- Topical Files, 1923-1972
  The bulk of the papers (23 linear feet) were accessioned in 1968, and are arranged as topical files, in chronological order by academic year, 1951-1967. These files cover the period Niehuss served as Vice President and Dean of Faculties (1951-1963) and executive Vice President (1962-1968). In addition to the yearly alpha files there are several special files including: Special Advisory Committee to the President on the Cases of Clement Markert, Mark Nickerson, and H. Chandler Davis, 1954; Deanship Search Files; 55 Million Dollar Fundraising Program File; Phoenix Project File; and Sesquicentennial File.
  The 1992 accession spans the years 1923-1971, and is arranged as one topical file. Of particular interest are the "Appropriation Requests to the Legislature, 1947-1968," which provide an annual summary of the university's financial needs and goals. Researchers with an interest in the administration's relations with the House Un-American Activities Committee should consult the "American Association of University Professors," "Communism," and "Special Advisory Committee" folders in the 1992 accession; and the 1954 topical files, the folder "The Three" in the 1955-56 topical files, and box 21 in the 1968 accession.
  The 2000 accession covers 1929 through 1972, and is arranged as one alphabetical file. Most of the files are topical, and consist of correspondence, reports and background materials on a subject, committee or organization. The accession also contains course outlines, notes and examination questions for two of Niehuss' classes: the Legal Problems of Higher Education seminar, and his Property class. There is also one folder of Personal materials, which includes news clippings, correspondence, and a transcript of a speech given to the Michigan Association of the Professions. Of particular note is the file "Compliance Review" which relates to university compliance issues surrounding the Civil Rights Act of 1964.
  - 1951-1952
    - A (Box 1)
    - Architecture and Design, College of (Box 1)
    - Athletic Association (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - Business Administration, School of (Box 1)
    - Dictionary of Middle English (Box 1)
    - Education, School of (Box 1)
    - Engineering College (Box 1)
    - Engineering Research (Box 1)
    - Engineering Research--Compensation (Box 1)
    - Engineering Research--Organization (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 1)
    - Graduate School (Box 1)
    - Grant Requests (Box 1)
    - Honorary Alumnus (Box 1)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 1)
    - Intercultural Relations, Committee on (Box 1)
    - K (Box 1)
    - L (Box 1)
    - Legislative Research Center (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - Medical School (Box 1)
    - P (Box 1)
    - Philippines, University of (Box 1)
    - R (Box 1)
    - Reactor (Box 1)
    - Scholarships (Box 1)
    - Senate, University (Box 1)
    - Soule, Malcolm H. (Box 1)
    - Tax Study--Proposed Ann Arbor Admissions Tax (Box 1)
    - Television (Box 1)
    - University Hospital (Box 1)
    - W (Box 1)
  - 1952-1953
    - A (Box 2)
    - Admissions (Box 2)
    - Alaska--University Aleutian Expedition (Box 2)
    - American Council on Education (Box 2)
    - Athletic Association (Box 2)
    - Automotive Laboratory (Box 2)
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - C (Box 2)
    - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Box 2)
    - College Relations, Committee on (Box 2)
    - Cross, R.N. (Box 2)
    - D (Box 2)
    - Development Council (Box 2)
    - Education, School of (Box 2)
    - Engineering College (Box 2)
    - Engineering Research (Box 2)
    - Ford Motor Company (Box 2)
    - G (Box 2)
    - Graduate School (Box 2)
    - Grant Requests (Box 2)
    - H (Box 2)
    - Hatcher, Harlan (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degree Committee (Box 2)
    - Institute for Human Adjustment (Box 2)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 2)
    - Institute of Industrial Health (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - K (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - Labor and Industrial Relations Meetings (Box 2)
    - Leaves, Sabbatical (Box 2)
    - Legislators (Box 2)
    - Library (Box 2)
    - Literary College (Box 2)
    - Medical School (Box 2)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 2)
    - Michigan State College (Box 2)
    - N.R.O.T.C. (Box 2)
    - Niehuss Reply to Governor Williams (Box 2)
    - Northwestern Michigan College (Box 2)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 2)
    - O (Box 2)
    - P (Box 2)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 2)
    - Presidents, Council of (Box 2)
    - Project Michigan (Box 2)
    - R (Box 2)
    - Regents (Box 2)
    - S (Box 2)
    - Senate, University (Box 2)
    - University Hospital
      - General (Box 2)
      - Children's Hospital (Box 2)
      - Hospital Board (Box 2)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 2)
      - Outpatient Clinic (Box 2)
    - Velde, Harold H. (Box 2)
    - Veterans' Hospital (Box 2)
    - Williams, R.L. (Box 2)
    - Willow Run Research (Box 2)
  - 1953-1954
    - A (Box 2)
    - Admissions (Box 2)
    - Alumni Association (Box 2)
    - Angell's Committee on Loyalty Cases (Box 2)
    - Association of Governing Board (Box 2)
    - Athletic Association (Box 2)
    - B (Box 2)
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - Building Development (Box 2)
    - Business Administration, School of (Box 2)
    - C (Box 2)
    - Candidates for University of Michigan Positions (Box 2)
    - College Relations, Committee on (Box 2)
    - Communism, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Computing Machinery, Association of (Box 2)
    - Cranbrook School--Board of Directors (Box 2)
    - Cross, R.N. (Box 2)
    - D (Box 2)
    - Development Council (Box 2)
    - E (Box 3)
    - Education, School of (Box 3)
    - Engineering, College of (Box 3)
    - Engineering--Nuclear (Box 3)
    - Engineering Research (Box 3)
    - Extension (Box 3)
    - F (Box 3)
    - Fellowship (Box 3)
    - Football Letters, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Ford Foundation Study in Behavioral Science (Box 3)
    - Francis, Thomas--Polio Project (Box 3)
    - G (Box 3)
    - Grant Requests (Box 3)
    - H (Box 3)
    - Hatcher, Harlan (Box 3)
    - Health Service (Box 3)
    - Higher Education, Conference on (Box 3)
    - Honorary Degrees, Committee on (Box 3)
    - Housing (Box 3)
    - I (Box 3)
    - Institute of Industrial Health (Box 3)
    - Internal Revenue Academy (Box 3)
    - J (Box 3)
    - K (Box 3)
    - Kresge Medical Research Building (Box 3)
    - L (Box 3)
    - Law School (Box 3)
    - Leaves, Sabbatical (Box 3)
    - Legislators (Box 3)
    - Legislators' Visit (Box 3)
    - Library (Box 3)
    - Literary College (Box 3)
    - Mc (Box 3)
    - M (Box 3)
    - Medical School (Box 3)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 3)
    - Michigan State College (Box 3)
    - Music, School of (Box 3)
    - Natural Resources, School of (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 3)
    - Philippine Institute Contract (Box 3)
    - Pierpont, W.K. (Box 3)
    - Presidents, Council of (Box 3)
    - Public Health, School of (Box 3)
    - Qualifications for Appointment and Promotion (Box 3)
    - R (Box 3)
    - Radio (Box 3)
    - Regents (Box 3)
    - Residence Halls (Box 3)
    - S (Box 3)
    - Scholarships (Box 3)
    - School Services, Bureau of (Box 3)
    - Senate, University (Box 3)
    - Senate Advisory Committee (Box 3)
    - Social Research, Institute for (Box 3)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 3)
    - State Bar of Michigan (Box 3)
    - Student-Faculty Meeting (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - Teaching Titles (Box 3)
    - Television (Box 3)
    - University Hospital
      - General (Box 3)
      - Hospital Board (Box 3)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 3)
    - V (Box 4)
    - Veterans Readjustment Center (Box 4)
    - W (Box 4)
    - Williams, R.L. (Box 4)
    - Willow Run Research (Box 4)
    - Woman in the World of Man (Box 4)
    - XYZ (Box 4)
  - 1954-1955
    - A (Box 4)
    - Admissions (Box 4)
    - Alumni Association (Box 4)
    - Business Administration, School of (Box 4)
    - C (Box 4)
    - Citizens Research Council (Box 4)
    - D (Box 4)
    - Deans' Conference (Box 4)
    - Dental School (Box 4)
    - Development Council (Box 4)
    - Education, School of (Box 4)
    - Engineering, College of (Box 4)
    - Engineering Research (Box 4)
    - F (Box 4)
    - Financing Capital Outlay in the Colleges (Box 4)
    - Flint, City of (Box 4)
    - Flint College--Advisory Planning Committee (Box 4)
    - G (Box 4)
    - Goldberg's Report on Fellowships and Scholarships (Box 4)
    - Grant Requests (Box 4)
    - H (Box 4)
    - Honorary Degrees, Committee on (Box 4)
    - Hospital Administration Program (Box 4)
    - Industrial Health, Institute of (Box 4)
    - K (Box 4)
    - Klein, Lawrence R. (Box 4)
    - L (Box 4)
    - Lama Temple (Box 4)
    - Legislators (Box 4)
    - Library (Box 4)
    - Literary College (Box 4)
    - M (Box 4)
    - McCarran Amendment (Box 4)
    - Medical School (Box 4)
    - Michigan Daily (Box 4)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 4)
    - Michigan State College-Name Change (Box 4)
    - Music, School of (Box 4)
    - N (Box 4)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 4)
    - Pierpont, W.K. (Box 4)
    - Political Science, Department of (Box 4)
    - Presidents, Council of (Box 4)
    - Project Michigan (Box 4)
    - Public Health, School of (Box 4)
    - R (Box 4)
    - Regents (Box 4)
    - Retail Credit Company (Box 4)
    - R.O.T.C. (Box 4)
    - S (Box 4)
    - Salk Vaccine (Box 4)
    - Senate, University (Box 4)
    - Social Research, Institute of (Box 4)
    - Social Security (Box 4)
    - T (Box 4)
    - Teaching Titles (Box 4)
    - Television (Box 4)
    - University Hospital (Box 4)
    - University Hospital--Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 4)
    - V (Box 4)
    - W (Box 4)
    - Williams, Robert L. (Box 4)
    - Willow Run Research (Box 4)
  - 1955-1956
    - A (Box 5)
    - Admissions (Box 5)
    - Alumni Association (Box 5)
    - Army-Mathematics Center (Box 5)
    - Athletic Association (Box 5)
    - B (Box 5)
    - Biederman, Les (Box 5)
    - Blue Cross (Box 5)
    - Building Space Needs (Plant Extension Committee) (Box 5)
    - Campbell-Ewald Research Project (Box 5)
    - Candidates for Positions (Box 5)
    - Certification Code for Teachers (Box 5)
    - Computing Center (Box 5)
    - Conference on University Contracts Abroad (Box 5)
    - Cost Survey (Box 5)
    - D (Box 5)
    - Data Processing Course for USAF Officers (Box 5)
    - E (Box 5)
    - Engineering
      - Automotive Engineering Laboratory (Box 5)
      - College of (Box 5)
      - Fluid Engineering Laboratory (Box 5)
      - Research Institute (Box 5)
    - F (Box 5)
    - Faculty Awards Committee (Box 5)
    - Flint Senior College (Box 5)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 5)
    - Ford Foundation Request--$1,050,000 (Box 5)
    - Foreign Operations Administration (Box 5)
    - Fund for the Advancement of Education (Box 5)
    - G (Box 5)
    - Gifts and Bequests (Box 5)
    - Grant Requests (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Research Institute (Box 5)
    - H (Box 5)
    - Hatcher, Harlan (Box 5)
    - Honorary Degrees, Committee on (Box 5)
    - Hospital Administration, Advisory Committee (Box 5)
    - I (Box 5)
    - IBM--G.C. Hurd (Box 5)
    - I.C.A. (Box 5)
    - Industrial Health, Institute of (Box 5)
    - Instructional Costs (Box 5)
    - J (Box 5)
    - K (Box 5)
    - Klein, Lawrence (Box 5)
    - L (Box 5)
    - Labor Education (Box 5)
    - Lectures (Box 5)
    - Literary College (Box 5)
    - Mc (Box 5)
    - M (Box 5)
    - Markert, Clement L. (Box 5)
    - Medical School (Box 5)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 5)
    - Museums Advisory Board (Box 5)
    - Music, School of (Box 5)
    - N (Box 5)
    - Newcomb, Theodore--Project (Box 5)
    - P (Box 5)
    - Philippines, University of (Box 5)
    - Pierpont, W.K. (Box 5)
    - Presidents, Council of (Box 5)
    - Project Michigan (Box 5)
    - R (Box 6)
    - Regents (Box 6)
    - Retirement at Age 70 (Box 6)
    - S (Box 6)
    - Security (Box 6)
    - Senate, University (Box 6)
    - Social Research, Institute for (Box 6)
    - Social Welfare Research, Coordinating Committee on (Box 6)
    - Social Security (Box 6)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 6)
    - Stacy, Robert H. [Haven Hall Arsonist] (Box 6)
    - T (Box 6)
    - Talks Given (Box 6)
    - The Three [House Un-American Activities Committee and Professors Nickerson, Davis and Markert] (Box 6)
    - Tenure Teaching Titles (Box 6)
    - University Hospital
      - General (Box 6)
      - Dr. R.D. Rabinovitch (Box 6)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 6)
    - Visitors (Box 6)
    - W (Box 6)
    - Wage and Salary Survey (Box 6)
    - Waseda University (Box 6)
    - Wayne University Study Commission (Box 6)
    - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 6)
    - Williams, R.L. (Box 6)
    - XYZ (Box 6)
  - 1956-1957
    - Architecture and Design, College of (Box 6)
    - Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (Box 6)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 6)
    - B (Box 6)
    - Blue Cross (Box 6)
    - Business, Small (Box 6)
    - D (Box 6)
    - Engineering--Marine Engineering and Naval Architecture (Box 6)
    - Engineering Research Institute (Box 6)
    - Faculty Awards Committee (Box 6)
    - Flint Senior College (Box 6)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 6)
    - Fund for the Advancement of Education (Box 6)
    - Geriatrics (Box 6)
    - Grand Rapids--Possible Medical School Site (Box 6)
    - Grant Requests (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Fishery Commission (Box 6)
    - Health Insurance Program--Students (Box 6)
    - Industrial Health, Institute of (Box 6)
    - International Cooperation Administration (Box 6)
    - International Geophysical Year (Box 6)
    - Labor Relations (Box 6)
    - Leaves for Junior Staff, Research (Box 6)
    - Literary College (Box 6)
    - Markert, Clement L. (Box 6)
    - Medical Research--Federal Aid (Box 6)
    - Medical School (Box 6)
    - Medical Science Building (Box 6)
    - Mental Health Research Michigan Health Council (Box 6)
    - Michigan State Medical Society (Box 6)
    - N (Box 7)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 7)
    - P (Box 7)
    - President's Commission on Education Beyond the High School (Box 7)
    - Presidents, Council of College (Box 7)
    - Project Michigan (Box 7)
    - Public Administration (Box 7)
    - R (Box 7)
    - Radiation Policy Committee (Box 7)
    - Russell Report (Box 7)
    - Scholarships (Box 7)
    - Senate, University (Box 7)
    - Senate Advisory Committee (Box 7)
    - Social Research, Institute for (Box 7)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 7)
    - T (Box 7)
    - Taxation and Business Report (Box 7)
    - TB--State Sanitarium--Surgical Program (Box 7)
    - University Hospital
      - General (Box 7)
      - Chronic Disease and Rehabilitation Hospital (Box 7)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 7)
    - University Policy, Committee on (Box 7)
    - Waseda (Box 7)
    - Wayne State University (Box 7)
    - Williams, Robert L. (Box 7)
  - 1957-1958
    - Architecture and Design (Box 7)